Guide to the Russian State Military Archives Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Russian state military archives collection
1918-1941
MS 1670
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10
The collection consists of photocopies of documents in the Russian State Military Archive (Rossiskii Gosudarstvennyi Voennyi Arkhiv) in Moscow. The documents relate to German-Soviet military and economic relations between 1918 and 1941, and the use of Soviet tanks in the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased with the assistance of the Smith Richardson Foundation and transferred from the International Security Program; gift of George Hofmann, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Other Finding Aids
For the original annotated list provided by the Russian Military Archives, which includes orginal document numbers, please see Original List.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of photocopies of documents in the Russian State Military Archive (Rossiskii Gosudarstvennyi Voennyi Arkhiv) in Moscow. The documents relate to German-Soviet military and economic relations between 1918 and 1941, and the use of Soviet tanks in the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and four additions: Series I: German-Soviet Military Cooperation, 1918-1934. Series II. Soviet Tanks in the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939.
Tank warfare; Tanks (Military science) -- Soviet Union; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939; Soviet Union -- Armed Forces; Germany -- Armed Forces; Germany -- Military relations -- Soviet Union; Soviet Union -- Military relations -- Germany
- German-Soviet Military Cooperation, 1918-1934; Series I
  - Letter from Antonov to Chicherin, 1918 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Handwritten letter from Antonov to Chicherin on a meeting with German officials.
  - Dispatch No. 1026 from M.I. Litvinov to G.V. Chicherin, 1920 June 23; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Dispatch N°1026 from M.I. Litvinov, Deputy People's Commissar of Foreign Affairs, to G.V. Chicherin, People'Commissar [hereafter Narkom] of Foreign Affairs, on a proposal to buy 100,000 military field flasks. Certified copy.
  - Telegram from E.M. Sklianskii to G.V. Chicherin, 1920 July 1; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Telegram from E.M. Sklianskii, Dep. chairman of the Military Revolutionary Council of the Republic [hereafter RVS], to G.V. Chicherin on the necessity of receiving rifles, machine guns and cartridges from Germany. Copy.
  - Letter from Victor Kopp to L.D. Trotskii, 1920 July 3; 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Letter from Victor Kopp, representative of the RSFSR for prisoner ofwar affairs in Germany, to L.D. Trotskii, Chairman of the RVS, on the possibility of transfeiring 5 airplanes from Germany to Russia. Autograph.
  - Telegram N° 3838/4/930/Sh from I.S. Unshlikht to L.D. Trotskii, 1920 August 19; 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Telegram N° 3838/4/930/Sh from I.S. Unshli..ld1t, member of RVS of the Zaparniy Front, to L.D. Trotskii on forthcoming proposals for buying German military equipment for 27 million marks. Resolution of Trotskii.
  - Letter from Viktor Kopp to E. Sklianskii, 1920 September 27; 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Letter from Viktor Kopp, representative of RSFSR in Germany for prisoner of war affairs, to E. Sklianskii on buying military equipment in Germany. Original.
  - Letter from Viktor Kopp on group of volunteers in Germany, 1920 November 10; 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Letter from Viktor Kopp on presence in Germany of a group of volunteers (former submarine commanders) desiring to enter into service in Russia. Resolution of L.D. Trotskii. Original.
  - Survey N° 7145 from the 2nd Section of the Red Army Staff, 1921 November 27; 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Survey N° 7145 from the 2nd Section of the Red Army Staff on the economic-financial relations of Germany and Soviet Russia. Original.
  - Report N° 7575 from Ya.K. Berzin to E.M. Sklianskii, 1921 December 15; 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Report N° 7575 from Ya.K. BelLin, head of the 2nd Section of the Red Army Staff, to E.M. Sklianskii on a proposal received to buy at a low price 300 field telephones of the latest German model. Resolution of Sklianskii. Original.
  - Report N° 1686/s. from Gol'dberg to Chairman L.D. Trotskii, 1922 February 24; 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Report N° 1686/s. from Gol'dberg to Chairman L.D. Trotskii on orders for uniforms and cloth in Germany. Original.
  - Letter N° 324 from Walter Lohmann to Ye.A. Berens, 1922 February 27 - March 3; 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter N° 324 from Walter Lohmann, head of the deparment of naval transport of the naval directorate of the Military Ministry [sic] of Germany, to Ye.A. Berens,naval expert attached to the plenipotentiary of the RSFSR in London, on perspectives for Soviet-German cooperation. Autograph in German. Russian text. Copy.
  - Letter N° 17/ber from Ye.A. Berens to L.D. Trotskii, 1922 April 21; 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter N° 17/ber., Berlin, from Ye.A. Berens to L.D. Trotskii on the question of transferring DobrFlot. Original.
  - Letter from A. Rozengol'ts to L.D. Trotskii, 1922 April 25; 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter from A. Rozengol'ts to L.D. Trotskii on the necessity for the acceleration of Russian-German talks on the organization of Russian military industry. Original.
  - RVS Order N° 1286, 1922 May 26; 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    RVS Order N° 1286 with declaration of Instructions concerning the ordering of regular flights for the German-Russian society for air communication between Moscow and Konigsberg.
  - Letter from George Koch Narkomat of Military Affairs, 1922 May 30; 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter from George Koch, German engineer, to Narkomat of Military Affairs with a proposal to use his invention in the area of small-arms technology. Conclusions of the Red Army Artillery Directorate. Original.
  - Reply letter N° 453/s. from Yordanskii to George Koch, 1922 July 5; 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Reply letter N° 453/s. from Yordanskii, military commissar of the Red Army Staff, to engineer George Koch apropos his proposal.
  - Letter from Walter Lohmann to the NKID, 1922 June 9 - August 28; 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter from Walter Lohmann from Berlin to the NKID on forthcoming two-sided talks concerning navigation. Copy. In German.
  - Report N°212 from Ye.A. Berens to V.I. Zof, 1922 August 20; 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Report N°212 from Ye.A. Berens to V.I. Zof, assistant to the Commander-in-Chief of the Navy, on talks with the German Admiralty. Copy.
  - Notification N° 17/r., 22/r. from Rozengol'ts to L.D. Trotskii, 1922 August 20; 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Notification N° 17/r., 22/r. from Rozengol'ts to L.D. Trotskii on the signed provisional agreement with Junkers and his conclusions on this agreement. Original and certified copy.
  - Report N° 189/s. from Gvait to A.P. Rozengol'ts, 1922 August 24 - 30; 19-20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Report N° 189/s. from Gvait, a military pilot, to A.P. Rozengol'ts and report N° 320 from A. Znamenskii, Main Chief of the Air Fleet of the Republic, to L.D. Trotskii with conclusions on the new proposal of the "Deruluft" society. Original.
  - Letter N° BG/040 from Gol'dberg to L.D. Trotskii, 1922 August 30; 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letter N° BG/040 from Gol'dberg from Berlin to L.D. Trotskii concerning a certain Kossarenko, a Soviet representative in Germany participating in a series of talks with German firms. Original.
  - Letter N° 301 from Ye.A. Berens to L.D. Trotskii, 1922 October 14; 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letter N° 301 from Ye.A. Berens to L.D. Trotskii on proposals of the Germany Admiralty. Original.
  - Letter N° 4955/s. from G.V. Chicherin to E.M. Sklianskii, 1922 October 22; 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letter N° 4955/s. from G.V. Chicherin to E.M. Sklianskii in connection with the German Admiralty's proposal. Certified copy.
  - Letter N° 264s. from Dessau to Rozengol'ts, 1922 October 24; 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letter N° 264s. from Dessau, representative of Junkers to Rozengol'ts in connection with the refusal to take AMO in concession. Certified copy.
  - Letter from the representative of Junkers to the directorate of the Red Air Fleet, 1922 October; 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letter from the representative of Junkers to the directorate of the Red Air Fleet concerning talks on the organization of a joint air route Moscow-Kharkov-Rostov-Tblisi. Copy.
  - Commercial proposal from Junkers Air Fleet of the RSFSR., 1922 October 31; 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Commercial proposal from Junkers to the Main Chief of the Air Fleet of the RSFSR. Translation from German.
  - Draft contract between Main Directorate of the Air Fleet and Junkers, 1922 November 3; 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Draft contract between the Main Directorate of the Air Fleet [hereafter Glavozdukhflot] and Junkers. Copy.
  - Supplementary protocol between the RSFSR and Junkers, 1922 November 3; 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Supplementary protocol to the contract on the delivery of airplanes concluded between the RSFSR and Junkers. Translation from German. Copy
  - Memorandum N° 7848 from M.M. Litvinov to E.M. Sklianskii, 1922 November 11; 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Memorandum N° 7848 from Dep. Narkom of Foreign Affairs M.M. Litvinov to E.M. Sklianskii on the forthcoming talks between RSFSR and Germany on the question of prize and embargo courts. Resolutions of E. Sklianskii.
  - Conclusion N° 242 of Glavozdukhflot, 1922 November 24; 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Conclusion N° 242 of Glavozdukhflot on Junker's proposal to deliver 60 airplanes to Russia. Resolution of A. Rozengol'ts. Otpusk.
  - Agreement N° 25121 s.s. between Glavozdukhflot and Junkers, 1922 December 12; 31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Agreement N° 25121 s.s. from 26 Nov. 1922 between Glavozdukhflot and Junkers. Certified copy.
  - Survey N° 58 on "Perspectives for German industry in the Russian Market", 1923 January 6; 32 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Survey N° 58 from the commercial representative of the RSFSR in Germany of the German press on "Perspectives for German industry in the Russian Market".
  - Extract N° 21951/s. Special commission to Berlin, 1923 January 22; 33 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Extract N° 21951/s. from a protocol of a meeting of the TsK RKP(b) on sending a special commission to Berlin.
  - Report N° 149/r. from A.P. Rozengol'ts to I.V. Stalin, 1923 January 25; 34 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Report N° 149/r. from A.P. Rozengol'ts to I.V. Stalin on the conditions leading to talks with the Germans.
  - Draft N° 429, 1923 February 1; 35 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Draft N° 429 "Of Basic Conditions for the Conclusion of an Agreement between NKPS and a German Automobile Concern". Certified copy.
  - Report from V. Stomaniakov to G.L.Piatakov, 1923 January; 36 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Report from V. Stomaniakov, the commercial representative of the RSFSR in Germany, to G.L.Piatakov, Chairman of the Main Concessionary Committee, on new proposals from German concerns and firms for concessions. Original.
  - Letter N° 205 from N. Krestinskii to the NKID and RVSR, 1923 February 13; 37 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter N° 205, Berlin, from N. Krestinskii to the NKID and RVSR on the composition of the German military commission travelling to Moscow.
  - Protocol N° 942/23 of a conference held by Junkers in Dessau, 1923 April 20; 38 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Protocol N° 942/23 of a conference held by Junkers in Dessau 16-17 April 1923 on the question of possible collaboration with Russia.
  - Survey N° 75 from the RSFSR in Germany of the German press, 1923 April 25; 39 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Survey N° 75, Berlin, from the commercial representative of the RSFSR in Germany of the German press on "F. Nansen on the Russian Problem" and "Russian-German Economic Dealings and the Russian Question".
  - Report N° 1312 from the RSFSR in Germany to L.B. Krasin, 1923 April 30; 40 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Report N° 1312, Berlin, from the commercial representative of the RSFSR in Germany to L.B. Krasin, Narkom of Foreign Trade, with a description of the German companies conducting commercial affairs with Russia. Supplement to the report--circular of a commercial industrial company (in German).
  - Note N° 228/1. from L.D. Trotskii to N.I. Muralov, 1923 May 5; 41 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Note N° 228/1. from L.D. Trotskii to N.I. Muralov, Commander of Forces in the MVO, concerning a report by V. Stomoniakov (from 30 April) and with a warning to be more vigilant in commercial affairs with German firms and companies. Certified copy.
  - Surveys N°N° 78, 80, from the RSFSR in Germany to the German press, 1923 May 14 - 30; 42-43 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Surveys N°N° 78, 80, Berlin, from the commercial representative of the RSFSR in Germany to the German press on the participation of Germany in the economic reconstruction of Russia. Typewritten specimen.
  - Letter and official note from A.P. Rozengol'ts to L.D. Trotskii and E.M. Sklianskii, 1923 May 26; 44-45 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter and official note from A.P. Rozengol'ts to L.D. Trotskii and E.M. Sklianskii on difficulties which had arisen for Junkers in the organization of production in Russia. Original.
  - Survey N° 87 from the RSFSR in Germany of the German press, 1923 June 5; 46 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Survey N° 87, Berlin, from the commercial representative of the RSFSR in Germany of the German press on the violation of the interests of German firms in Soviet Russia. Typewritten specimen.
  - Memo report N° 2070/2526 ss. from A.P. Rozengol'ts to E.M. Sklianskii, 1923 July 2; 47 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Memo report N° 2070/2526 ss. from A.P. Rozengol'ts, the main chief of the Air Fleet of the Republic to E.M. Sklianskii with a conclusion on the entry of Dobrolet into Deruluft, an air service implemented between Moscow and Germany. Original.
  - Letter from Stachevskii to A.P. Rozengol'ts, 1923 August 31; 48 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter from Stachevskii to A.P. Rozengol'ts on the conditions of work by Junkers. 6 September, cover letter from A.P. RozengoI'ts to L.D. Trotskii. Copy.
  - Letter from the USSR to A.P. Rozengol'ts, 1923 October; 49 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter from the commercial representative of the USSR in Germany to A.P. Rozengol'ts on the aerodrome in Polotsk. Copy.
  - Resolutions N° 2383 and N° 3060 of the NKID and Red Army Staff, 1924 February 29 - March 13; 50 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Resolutions N° 2383 and 3060 of the NKID and Red Army Staff (and P.P. Lebedev, Chief of the Red Army Staff), on the draft consular convention between the USSR and Germany. Certified copy. Original.
  - Letter from B. Kuksin to the Main Inspector of the Civil Air Fleet, 1924 May 18 - June 22; 51 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letter from B. Kuksin, engineer of air services and employee of Moscow delegation to Junkers, to the Main Inspector of the Civil Air Fleet with a request to send him on an official trip abroad to carry out scientific work. Original.
  - Letter N° 5326 from Junkers, 1924 May 18 - June 22; 52 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letter N° 5326, Moscow, from Junkers with a supportive petition by B. Kuksin. Original.
  - Memorandum N° 47872 from the the Civil Air Fleet to the NKVD, 1924 May 18 - June 22; 53 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Memorandum N° 47872 from the Main Inspector of the Civil Air Fleet to the visa department of the NKVD with a supportive petition by Kuksin. Certified copy.
  - Correspondence from V.I. Zof with I.S. Unshlikh, 1924 June 19; 54-56 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence from V.I. Zof, commissar of Naval Forces of the Republic, with I.S. Unshlikht, Dep. Chairman of the RVS, on a proposal received from Germany concerning the purchase of submarines. Technical data for German submarines. Autographs.
  - Conclusions of the NKPS on German and Soviet railways, 1924 July 18 - September 23; 57-58 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Conclusions of the NKPS, Legal Department of the Red Army and Directorate of Military Communications of the Red Army Staff (N°N° 23/2790/s.; 12996s./1293s.; 342374/s.; 13031/s.; -7/2/342945/s.) on the direct transfer of cargo between German and Soviet railways (Konigsberg direction railroads are suggested). Originals and otpuski.
  - Radiograms in German, 1924 August 6; 59 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reference N° 781/P., 1925 February 5; 60 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Reference N° 781/P. on the changes of the political course of the German government after the adoption of the Dawes Plan and the state of German-Soviet military relations; sent to M.V. Frunze. Certified copy.
  - Information sent to M.V. Frunze, 1925 February 22; 61 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Information, sent to M.V. Frunze, on the presence (in a report of the InterUnion Control Commission) of data concerning the fulfillment of military orders of the USSR with private German firms. Certified copy.
  - Survey of the contents of a report by Marshal Foch's Military Committee, 1925 March 3; 62 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Survey of the contents of a report by Marshal Foch's Military Committee on the results of the control on Germany's military industry; sent to M.V. Frunze. Certified copy.
  - Memo report from P.I. Baranov to L.G. Ginzburg, 1925 March 5; 63 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Memo report from P.I. Baranov, i.d. Chief of the Military Air Forces of the Red Army, to L.G. Ginzburg on the interests of the UVVS in dirigible building in Germany. Original.
  - Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze, 1925 March 10; 64 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze on a visit to the Junkers aviation factory in Dessau, on acquaintance with new inventions in the area of instrument-making, and on talks held with the firm Telefunken. Original.
  - Report from Ya.M. Fishman to M.V. Frunze, 1925 March 20; 65 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Report from Ya.M. Fishman, Chief of the Military-Chemical Directorate of the Red Army, to M.V. Frunze, Chairman of the RVS USSR, on a conversation with Hasse and Fischer, representatives of the German Reichswehr, on the possibility of becoming acquainted with the designing of aerial bombs and gas sprayers. Original.
  - Report from Ya.M. Fishman to M.V. Frunze, 1925 April 3; 66 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Report from Ya.M. Fishman to M.V. Frunze, Chairman of the RVS USSR, on a visit to an Auer gas mask factory and on a conversation with Fischer; Reichswehr representative, concerning the possibility of joint work in the area of chemical weapons. Copy.
  - Protocol of Soviet-German agreement, 1925 April 15; 67 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Protocol of Soviet-German agreement on the organization of an aviation school in Lipetsk. Copy.
  - Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze, 1925 April 17; 68 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze on the preparation for tests of new models of German rifles and the course of talks with the Anilin concern on the rendering of technical help to the USSR. Certified copy.
  - Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze, 1925 April 21; 69 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze on the necessity to include nitrogen and dye industry in the "large program" of collaboration with Germany and on the status of the purchase of weapons for foreign countries. Certified copy.
  - Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze, 1925 May 4; 70 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze on the loading on steamships of the airplanes, military equipment and arms purchased in Germany. Original.
  - Extract from protocols of meetings of the RVS SSSR from 22 Dec. 1924, 1925 May 8; 71 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Extract from protocols of meetings of the RVS SSS from 22 Dec. 1924 with the resolutions on the necessity for continuing collaboration with Junkers. Certified copies.
  - Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze, 1925 May 14; 72 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze on the beginning of work by the commission for the formal acceptance of optics and gas masks that were ordered; and on talks concerning collaboration with the Karo concern for the rebuilding of nitrous industrial works in the USSR. Certified copy.
  - Extract from a protocol of a meeting of the Main Concessionary Committee in the SNK USSR, 1925 May 21; 73 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Extract from a protocol of a meeting of the Main Concessionary Committee in the SNK USSR on a report concerning talks with the joint-stock company Junkers with a resolution about a change in conditions for a contract concluded earlier. Certified copy.
  - Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze, 1925 May 26; 74 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letter from Yakov Fishman to M.V. Frunze on talks taking place with representatives of German industrial firms concerning the organization of joint production of military technology. Certified copy.
  - Extract from a protocol of a meeting of the RVS USSR, 1925 June 2; 75 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Extract from a protocol of a meeting of the RVS USSR with a resolution on consent to revise the concessionary contract with Junkers at the request of the concessionaire on condition of the adoption of the terms of the RVS USSR. Certified copy. (RVS press).
  - Memo report from SNK USSR to I.V. Stalin, 1925 June 2; 76 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Memo report of the Main Concessionary Committee in the SNK USSR (Glavkontsesskom) to the Politbiuro TsK [hereafter Politburo] I.V. Stalin on the necessity for revising the contract concluded with Junkers. Original.
  - Memorandum from the VVS Directorate to the head of the UVVS, 1925 June 4; 77 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Memorandum from the concessionary department of the VVS Directorate to the head of the UVVS with conclusions on the course of talks with Junkers concerning the introduction of changes into the contract on collaboration. Copy.
  - Letter from the Junkers representative to M.V. Frunze and L.D. Trotskii, 1925 June 6; 78 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letter from the Junkers representative to M.V. Frunze and L.D. Trotskii, chairman of the Glavkontsesskom, on the speeding up a decision of the question of introducing changes into the contract on collaboration that was concluded earlier. Original in German; translation into Russian.
  - Letter N° 27 from Sachsenberg, 1925 June 9; 79 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letter N° 27 from Sachsenberg, representative of Junkers, with an account of the proposals on the introduction of changes into the contract concluded earlier dealing with a serial order for airplanes. Translated from German.
  - Letter N° 0032 from Sachsenberg to Frunze, 1925 June 11; 80 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letter N° 0032 from Sachsenberg to Frunze providing the reasons for the introduction of changes into the contract on collaboration from 1922 and the necessity for speeding up a decision on this question by Glavkontsesskom. Original.
  - Letter from the Junkers representative to Frunze, 1925 June 13; 81 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letter from the Junkers representative to Frunze with proposals on the introduction of changes into the contract on collaboration with the firm; with a cover memorandum to Glavkontsesskom. Original in German. Translation in Russian.
  - Memo report N° 9270 ss. from the Red Army VVS to the RVS USSR, 1925 June 15; 82 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Memo report N° 9270 ss. from the Directorate of the Red Army VVS to the chairman of the RVS USSR on the non-fulfillment by Junkers of orders for Ju-20 and Ju-21 airplanes in the prescribed time; with an enclosure on the tactical data for these airplanes. Original.
  - Memo report N° 3365 ss. from P.I. Baranov to Frunze, 1925 June 15; 83 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Memo report N° 3365 ss. from P.I. Baranov, head of the Directorate of Military Air Forces, to Frunze on the terms of the serial order for airplanes and the introduction of changes into the concessionary contract with Junkers; with a protocol of a meeting at the UVVS from 30 May 1925 on this question as an enclosure. Original.
  - Memo report N° 21/ss. from Baranov to Frunze, 1925 June 16; 84 (Box 1, Folder 8)